Welcome to the second episode of Under the Hood.
So in the first episode we talked about AI and
how we develop AI features in Business Central.
And short after we released this episode, we put out
a small poll on social media where we asked you
what you wanted to hear about in this series that
we proposed several topics and the compiler 1.
So today with me I've Espen who is the architect
behind the L compiler.
But before we get into the details of the inner
working on the the L compiler, let's start with a
brief history we we we had before the L compiler
and VS Code we had Seaside, and I'm sure some
of you remember Seaside.
So Aspen, have you?
Have you worked with Seaside?
Yes, I have actually worked a lot with Seaside.
I have spent most of my time at Microsoft as
a part of the NAV team, but actually the first
thing I did in the NAV team was that I
was sent over from the team I worked on, which
was the old business Microsoft Business Framework team to help
creating a prototype of the new client on top of
Seaside or what would become the 3T architecture.
And we actually produced a video for Steve Balmer, which
was it felt like a big thing back then and.
So there was we had like by then we had
like a 2T architecture.
Yes, the old C side were two tier.
It was a client development environment, everything in one towing
directly to the database.
Yeah.
So there was no, yeah, that's true.
The client and the development environment were in the same
in the same.
Application exactly.
And then when I joined the team, I worked a
lot on the server side of it and actually also
the compilation from the old CL code into the C#
code that was the foundation for the new 3T architecture.
So C side was written in C, right?
In, yeah, actually a mix of C&C because.
C&C.
Yes, it was worse than C and it was.
Well, it has its own memory manager and own error
handling, not exception based as you could have done in
C So it was a very slow process to develop
new features.
And so very costly to add new features.
Yes.
So there's no doubt that at some stage she side
was due for a, you know?
A modernization or a organization or replacement, yes.
But it was hard because we had, so we talked
about it many times.
Yes, we did.
We have those talks over many years.
The last one I remember was in 2014.
I think we were a team who was tasked with
figuring out what should come next and we actually recently
looked at the old conclusions.
Then it was all about speedy delivery, modelized, best of
class development environment marketplace.
There was a lot of things which actually turned out
to be what we have today.
It's all the concepts we.
It was a nice vision document back then, but we
have no plans of how we would proceed.
It was the vision we actually did that year.
And it was also difficult because we have.
First of all, on code base is pretty big and
rewriting it and and and you know to a new
language would be like tremendous effort.
Yes.
And also there's a lot of code out there, you
know, a lot of partners and millions and millions, a
lot of code.
And we, we didn't want to disrupt them, right?
Exactly So what we looked at the year after was
I I built a small prototype and it was actually
shown at Tech Days in 2015 by from Saisburg and
it was essentially a small Winforms app where we loaded
in a TXT file from export if I think the
safe post code unit and you could make changes to
it and it instantly gave passing diagnostics in the UI.
It was most of all a nice picture of what
could be a compiler someday.
It was not.
It was pretty far from what we needed.
OK.
But then you had, you had this brilliant idea how
to transition from, you know, having these large codebase including
our own, including our base app and but also the,
you know, the the panel code was how we could
transition from that to A to a new model, a
new development environment.
Yeah.
And in the beginning it was.
I mean the brilliant idea come out of necessity because
we had, I mean our base app is so big
and we knew that it will take years before we
were actually able to compile it.
So we had to figure out how we could start
working with this, get feedback.
So the idea was that because we have decided that
our new language would be modulized so we knew that
we would introduce dependencies between modules.
And we have already created a format for that which
were the reference symbol information that we store on the
top in in the app files.
And the idea was that we could just use Seaside
to create a similar symbolic symbolic format and based on
the base app.
But now we have what is needed for AL to
work on top.
So kind of wrapping it in something that would look
like So from the outside it would look like it
was the new code, but underneath it was the old
code and then we could start working on top of
that with the new tools, right?
Exactly.
And that allows us to ship early previews of it.
And we did that for a couple of years, and
the initial one was only we could create simple code
units, simple tables, pages.
And then we also introduced table extensions and page extensions
for that, so you could already there.
We wanted to promote the new model.
With so you could write extensions already.
Our partners could write extensions.
We also had a few third first party extension I
believe, but our own code base didn't compile yet with
the new tool.
No, and it it took a couple of years.
In 2019, in wave two, we shipped the first AL
compiler without the preview mark on it, and then at
that time we could compile all our objects.
We could do most, but we haven't converted our own
pay set yet.
It took another year because we have an insane amount
of dependencies on how we did stuff internally, so it
took another year before we could actually ship completely without.
So, so let's go really under the hood now.
So when when you started working on this new compiler,
we needed an architecture.
Yes.
And I think we 2015 was the perfect storm for
this because C# the year before has actually released Rosslyn.
They have gone through some of the similar thought processes
even though they were a better starting point than us.
So Rosslyn was the new C# compiler.
Like a totally new rewritten compiler actually, wasn't it?
Exactly.
Actually the original C# compiler was written in, I guess
C++ and something like that.
Just like us.
Just like us and they moved to C#.
So it's basically compiling yourself approach, but that was a
smaller part of it.
The more important part was that they realized that they
already have a.
They have one compiler for a command line and almost
a similar compiler that were used inside Visual Studio to
provide intellisense and all that.
And they merged that into one and or a componentized
solution where they could use the compiler as a service.
So the same compiler, the same base part of the
compiler that serves the command line compilation is also the
one that constantly runs in the background and provides intellisense,
cross references.
All the things we like to have in a modern
environment.
That's the was lean architecture.
Yes, that was the architecture We also, I mean took
a great deal of inspiration from because.
I mean, so you looked at it and say, OK,
that's that's a good idea.
That's a really good idea.
We want to have that as well.
Yes, let's.
Do some.
So we just to be clear, we we didn't reuse
any of the code, did we?
Not such.
Not we just use the architecture.
It's not Roslyn, but we have moved a lot of
the concepts out of the Roslyn code base because we
are not.
We're not a true.net language, so we couldn't just build.
I mean Rosslyn already contains the b.net C# and also
F# based on the same core libraries, but it's they
are all true.net languages and we are not.
So we pulled out the stuff we needed, augmented it
and built a lot more on top in in some
sense because we have way more concepts than C# for
instance.
So in some some sense we are more complicated because
we have I mean 7-8 top level symbols where C#
have class enum stroked.
So we have pages tables.
Exactly.
So we have a lot more differences in our in
our.
Version.
So you talked about the perfect storm.
You meant sorry.
By that you meant there was a Ross link compiler.
And also Visual Studio Code 1.
When we pitched the original one in 2015, Visual Studio
Code was in version 0.6 and was very immature but
very promising and we decided to bet on that and
it fit also very nicely with.
With the Rosslyn architecture we we we used and before
that we actually if we have started out coding the
year before we wouldn't have probably done it right.
But this time we, I mean we have these two
great components to lean against and it it's a really,
really nice architecture.
Just to be clear on one end, there's the worst
link compiler, the worst link architecture, Yes, And.
But it has nothing to do actually with Visual Studio
Code.
It's just an independent architecture, Yes.
Actually when we when you run, when you compile, say
from the command line, it goes through this pipeline, this
architecture, yes.
And it's totally independent Visual Studio Code, right.
Exactly.
But you call it the perfect storm, because on one
hand we had this great development environment, which Visual Studio
Code is, and then the Roseland architecture.
So we took inspiration from one and build it into
the other.
And then that's how the new tool set was born.
Yes, and we knew that Visual Studio Code was an
early beta at that point, but we also realized that
we could easily repurpose A compiler to another environment if
we had to.
But turned out that best decision ever to bet on
Visual Studio Code because it's have turned out to be
the gift that keeps on giving for us.
We get new features every year or every month and
we can easily adopt to them, so.
Yeah, there's a lot of advantages of being in Visual
Studio Code.
Has a lot of.
Leverage all the all the things that it offers.
And that allows us to focus on what is important
for us, which is our language, the concepts that we
need for the platform, rather than inventing a lot of
UI for showing intelligence and all that.
Things like that, yeah, we get most of that for
free.
So you mentioned the that we have a language service
as part of it, which is kind of what the
roles in architecture also has.
So how is that a good thing?
Why do we need a language service?
We need a language service because modern developers actually expect
to be able to get into the sense get information
about the symbols in the editor.
So whenever you type, we need the compiler to run
instantly in the background.
But that's what the language service does.
Yes, exactly So it has the set of all files,
and it constantly provides a new compilation that.
Even partial compilations.
Even partial comp.
Typically when you type, by definition you are you know
it's like you've written half of the code, you or
less, and then typically doesn't compile.
Most of the time when you're in the compiler, what
you have written in your it does not compile exactly,
so it requires.
It requires the background compilation to be able to do
some partial.
Compilations for the utilis and something like that would be
good at recovery.
That's actually one of the harder parts because it's.
I mean, it's textbook to create a compiler that has
a perfect source, but but having a source where you
are typing something in the middle but you would still
like to have intellisense for what comes after means that
you need to do recovery.
And another important aspect of that is also that when
you only make more changes, you don't want to repass
everything, you want to reuse as much as possible to
be memory efficient in the background compilation.
Yeah, so it's you have good performance and a good
experience as a developer.
And that's actually one of the places where we really
benefited from what we got from Roslyn, because it's helped
us be efficient there.
And the language services also an integral part of Visual
Studio Code and how they envision that you extend Visual
Studio Code with other languages.
So that's the architecture they recommend if you want to
implement a new language.
Yes, and they actually invented what is called the Language
Service Protocol exactly for this.
And it's a description of the communication between an editor
and between languages.
And the idea is that as long as you adhere
to the LSP, you can replace languages or you can
replace a sense.
That's actually a standard of an open source protocol, isn't.
It it is an open source protocol and it's very
efficient and it it's it's they come often come with
new additions to it that we can then uptake and
we can add support for that in our language server.
So we suddenly support new features invented in Visual Studio
Code.
So when when we, when we started modernizing the old
development environment and and starting you know, kind of revamping
the language, we we could have chosen an existing language
like we could have chosen, I don't know, TypeScript, JavaScript
or even Python.
Then we wouldn't have had to write a, a a
compiler because there are compilers out there that.
So why?
Why?
Why didn't we do that?
Oh, there's a couple of reasons, and one of the
reasons is that we we we need a sandbox language.
Since we are running third party code on our servers,
we need something that we could control to the.
Security reasons, for example.
Yes, so.
So we it's not an option for us to go
directly to dot net.
We need to somehow use the language as a barrier
or having a trusted runtime for it that that was
one of the reasons.
The other reason is that we have, I mean we
could go through the process of converting our own pace
to any language potentially it.
That's still a lot of work.
Still a lot of work and the result may not
be as easy to work with and actually would end
up not having the same connection between data and metadata
that we have.
I mean we have the which is rather unique in
my opinion.
You can.
You can stand on a table field and you can
get cross references for all the places where it's used.
This is a language that's been written for for ERP
and for Business Central.
Exactly.
But the most important part of this was that our
entire partner channel have invested in this language.
So we actually have gone through great work to preserve
as much of their IP as possible in the process.
We know that from time to time, yes, we have
asked our channel to make changes.
We don't like it and we know that they definitely
don't like it.
We do have breaking changes, but.
We do have.
We do what we can to preserve.
I mean if you look at the whole history of
of of NAV and Business Central, we've went through a
lot of efforts to preserve this code base throughout all
these years.
Maybe that could be the topic of another under the
hood talks, actually.
Yeah, it is actually something we have spent a lot
of time on over the years, yes.
So you you said that that we're not a AL
is not a true NET language.
However, the L compiler is not is not exactly compiler.
We're not compiling in the pure sense of the word,
meaning we're not producing executable bytes and bits and bytes
and artifacts that can that can be executed directly on
the on on the operating system.
We it's more of a transpire, right?
We are converting AL to C#.
Is that a good idea?
Yes, I think for us it is we, we this
is what we did originally in C side.
So C side did the same thing.
Yes, C side did the same thing.
And when we started out, we we couldn't also take
upon the task too compiled directly to IL.
It's hard.
It would be harder for us to verify, it would
be harder for us to debug.
So we chose that.
If we just did what C sent did, the runtime
would actually work, even though we had a new compiler.
So what what happened?
When I have a snippet of code, the compiler takes
it and the L compiler takes it and actually generates
some C# code that basically does the same thing but
in C#, and then we compile the C code after
that to an actual execute using the regular C compiler,
right?
Yes, and that's exactly what we're doing.
And then we have some additional metadata.
We actually put in most cases XML and also stall
Mac in the runtime or in the database.
So this is what we use for execution.
So back to VS Code and back to the the
paradigm shift from from Seaside to to AL.
There was another.
So we we went from from Seaside to to BS
Code.
That was 1 paradigm shift.
But there was another pretty significant paradigm shift that we
went through.
At that stage we went from a repository based source
source artifacts to a text file based artifacts.
So before in Seaside when you, the code you wrote
was actually stored in the database, yes?
And now with with Visual Studio Code and with the
L compiler, the code is actually saved in text file
like any like many other languages like C# and JavaScript
and so forth.
Is that is that was that a good thing or?
Yeah, in my opinion it was definitely a good thing.
I earlier on in my tenure in Navy I worked
on modernizing the build pipeline for for the application and
and me and a colleague was taskbar to work with
that.
And at that point in time all the sources were
exported from Seaside into the TXT file and then they
had to use a small B application that using automation
on top of Seaside to create database, import object, compile
all objects which was horrible to automate.
So the first the thing we actually did was to
just turn Seaside into give Seaside a command line so
you could actually compile from the command line.
It was not pretty, but it was better than what
it was.
And from that point on I just dreamt about fixing
this for real because it was it was not nice
to to work with it.
Well, and there there's a lot of advantages of having
the source code in texts, because there's a lot of
tools out there which you know, like source source control
to like git or and and you know, searching if
you want to search through the through the code, right?
There's a lot of search tools and you know that.
Yes.
And when you work, yeah.
And when you work with, with repositories like Git or
DevOps, we also now have syntax highlight in there.
So you can actually better, yeah exactly inspect your source
code.
So there's a lot of benefits from that.
And also there wasn't, I mean there was sort of
a parallel effort to our cloud endeavor at that point
in time.
But it also turns out that, I mean having the
requirement to talk directly to a database in the cloud
is a very bad idea.
And so it it matches that as well.
So another thing that happened when we moved from Seaside
to Visual Studio Code is that we lost.
We had some designers in the in Seaside and and
these designers disappeared.
We went to again a fully text based approach where
instead of describing things through these designers, you would have
to describe them in, in in the text file directly
in the in the file where you had your code
right.
And we we we got a lot of feedback on
this.
People are still asking about it.
So, but yeah, then you had another another great idea
about that.
Yes, I have.
The last couple of years I have focused a lot
on trying to figure out how we can make our
biggest API which is our basic, more visible, better discoverable,
navigable.
And one of the ideas I wanted to explore was
if if we somehow could use the Web view feature
in Visual Studio Code in combination with our language server
to to actually put some UI on top of our
application objects.
So just to explain a little bit, the the web
view feature in Visual Studio Code, it's actually a page
that you can have like normally in Visual Studio Code,
when you open a file, it's typically a text file
that will show the content of the file.
But the Visual Studio Code has this feature where you
can actually have a page which is in essence a
browser and you can display HTML in it.
So you can display pretty advanced UI in it and
this page can communicate with other regular text pages like
for example you can have you know.
A good example is that I think many people are
familiar with is.
If you open a read me file, you can see
the markup language in a text file and you can
see the preview of it in the actual formatted way.
They actually have Visual Studio Code have two concepts.
They have one which is a web view disconnected from
source.
Then they have the custom design, I think web view,
and the what we shipped first was actually AL Explorer
and ALE Home.
They are built on just being a web view disconnected
from source.
But the AL Explorer is using actually the same grid
as our analysis view to show all the objects and
they get the information from the running compilation.
So it's not statically.
When you go and edit something in a file somewhere,
it also shows up because it's running.
So that's a page in in the L Explorer.
That's a page in Visual Studio Code that allows you
to actually navigate your code, and you can do some.
We'll put a link in in in the comments on
the documentation of the L Explorer, right?
And also we added Alhome which is the which is
a news feed for developers, business central AI developers where
we where that suddenly have a way of communicating the
IT directly with with with our developers which is a
nice new feature.
But also, and I know you remember that because we
were on the same session and directions Mia and Hamburg
where I showed up of a couple of designers, table
designer, page designers.
They are built on the other model, the custom designer
model, which actually is a visualization of the source code,
which means that if you make changes through the designer,
it updates the.
Song.
So that's the old designers.
That was.
Actually in a new Visual Studio Code.
Environment.
But that's still a prototype.
Right, still a prototype.
I would love us to prioritize them, but again, we
need to prioritize.
So but it shows it can be done with this
functionality.
So we have some ideas on how to maybe revive
these designers at some stage right?
But it's still the prototype label.
So one last thing, we we also have a lot
of people asking us to expose the compiler as an
API.
They would like to be able to use it to
do all sorts of things and some people actually doing
it already in a kind of non supported way.
Is that something we we are going to do?
There, from the beginning when we started creating a new
compiler, it based on the browsing model.
It's envisioned as a service we haven't officially opened up
for.
New for for external use means that we haven't documented
it, but we know there's a lot of partners out
there that are actually.
We're not preventing it.
No, we're not preventing it.
We're not just supporting it and we we reserve ourselves
the right to change it at any time.
And we actually, I mean we try not to break
anything.
Also here, even though we haven't officially supported, we actually
we know that it's used and it's used for the
benefit of our community, which is great and I love
why we don't.
Prevent it.
And I love to see all the things which are
actually.
People are doing pretty good cool things with it, right?
Yes, exactly.
And as I mean already incredibly many AL related extensions
in the Visual Studio Code Marketplace, which is amazing to
see the ideas and creativity that our partner Jung is
actually adding also in the development area.
All right.
So if maybe to conclude, I would ask you, if
you know, if I'm a new developer and I'm mute,
we are new to Business Central, what would you recommend?
Where do I Where do I start?
How do I get started with developing, you know, extensions
for for for Business Central?
Yeah, there's of course our own documentation on Ms.
learning, which is both a combination of reference documentation but
also getting started documentation.
And then there's our launch event videos and which also
talks about all the new features and sometimes also a
little bit broader and actually our partner channel also here
doing it and amazing work.
I mean we have many partners blogging or creating videos
around development.
So lots of resources out there.
There's lots of resources which are, I mean really great
resources, and it's also really great to see how many
actually want to contribute and make this an even better
community.
It's a really great community we have out there.
Thank you.
Thank you for supporting us.
Yes.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Thank you, Espen.
I hope you enjoy this talk about the inner workings
of the L compiler.
Let us know in the comments next time.
Next time we'll talk about, we'll try to answer the
question of how many users can Business Central handle in
the cloud.
So stay tuned and thank you for watching.